<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>com.vintagetechie.CosmicExtAppletTempest</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-only</project_license>
  <project_group>COSMIC</project_group>
  <name>Tempest</name>
  <name xml:lang="uk">Буря</name>
  <summary>Weather applet for COSMIC Desktop with automatic location detection</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="cs">Applet počasí pro prostředí COSMIC s automatickým určením polohy</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="uk">Віджет погоди COSMIC із автоматичним визначенням місцезнаходження</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Tempest is a weather applet for the COSMIC Desktop environment that provides
      real-time weather information with automatic location detection. It displays
      current conditions, temperature, and AQI directly in your panel.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">
      Tempest je applet počasí pro prostředí COSMIC, který poskytuje
      aktuální informace o počasí s automatickým určením polohy. Zobrazuje
      aktuální podmínky, teplotu a kvalitu ovzduší přímo v panelu.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">
      Tempest -- віджет погоди для середовища COSMIC, який надає актуальну
      інформацію про погоду з автоматичним визначенням місцезнаходження.
      Відображає поточні умови, температуру та індекс якості повітря безпосередньо на панелі.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">Funkce:</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Особливості:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Real-time weather data from Open-Meteo API (no API key required)</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Aktuální data o počasí z Open-Meteo API (není potřeba API klíč)</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Дані про погоду в реальному часі з Open-Meteo API (без ключа API)</li>
      <li>Automatic location detection via IP geolocation</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Automatické určení polohy pomocí geolokace IP</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Автоматичне визначення місцезнаходження через IP</li>
      <li>Saved locations with quick switching (up to 8 bookmarks)</li>
      <li>Panel display toggles for icon, temperature, AQI, pressure, dew point, and sunrise/sunset</li>
      <li>Tabbed popup interface with weather, air quality, alerts, forecasts, and settings</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Rozbalovací okno se záložkami pro počasí, kvalitu ovzduší, výstrahy, předpovědi a nastavení</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Вкладковий інтерфейс із погодою, якістю повітря, сповіщеннями, прогнозами та налаштуваннями</li>
      <li>Current conditions including temperature, feels-like, and humidity</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Aktuální podmínky včetně teploty, pocitové teploty a vlhkosti</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Поточні умови: температура, відчуття, вологість</li>
      <li>Wind information with speed, direction compass, and gusts</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Informace o větru: rychlost, směr a nárazy</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Інформація про вітер: швидкість, напрямок, пориви</li>
      <li>UV index, cloud cover, visibility, and atmospheric pressure</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">UV index, oblačnost, viditelnost a atmosférický tlak</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">УФ-індекс, хмарність, видимість, атмосферний тиск</li>
      <li>Sunrise and sunset times with timezone support</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Časy východu a západu slunce s podporou časového pásma</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Час сходу та заходу сонця з підтримкою часових поясів</li>
      <li>Air quality data with PM2.5, PM10, ozone, NO2, and CO readings</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Data o kvalitě ovzduší: PM2.5, PM10, ozón, NO2 a CO</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Дані якості повітря: PM2.5, PM10, озон, NO2, CO</li>
      <li>Auto-detects US or European AQI standard based on location</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Automatické rozpoznání amerického nebo evropského standardu AQI podle polohy</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Автоматичний вибір стандарту AQI США або Європи залежно від місцезнаходження</li>
      <li>Weather alerts for US (NWS), Canada (ECCC), Europe (MeteoAlarm), and Australia (BOM) with desktop notifications</li>
      <li>Hourly forecast with precipitation probability</li>
      <li>7-day forecast with high/low temperatures</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Předpověď na 7 dní s maximálními/minimálními teplotami</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Прогноз на 7 днів з мін./макс. температурою</li>
      <li>Auto or manual unit selection for temperature (F/C), measurement system, and pressure (hPa/inHg/PSI)</li>
      <li>Custom location support (latitude/longitude)</li>
      <li xml:lang="cs">Podpora vlastní polohy (zeměpisná šířka/délka)</li>
      <li xml:lang="uk">Введення координат вручну</li>
      <li>Adjustable refresh interval with network-aware retry</li>
      <li>Persistent configuration including last active tab</li>
      <li>Localized in multiple languages via Weblate</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Tempest is an independent, third-party project. It is not affiliated with,
      endorsed by, or sponsored by System76, Inc. "COSMIC" is a trademark of
      System76, Inc. Tempest is built for the COSMIC™ desktop using the public
      libcosmic framework.
    </p>
  </description>
  <url type="homepage">https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest/-/issues</url>
  <url type="donation">https://ko-fi.com/vintagetechie</url>
  <url type="translate">https://hosted.weblate.org/engage/tempest/</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest</url>
  <url type="changelog">https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest/-/blob/main/CHANGELOG.md</url>
  <developer_name>John Crenshaw</developer_name>
  <update_contact>john@vintagetechie.com</update_contact>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">com.vintagetechie.CosmicExtAppletTempest.desktop</launchable>

  <categories>
    <category>Utility</category>
    <category>COSMIC</category>
  </categories>

  <releases>
    <release version="2.9.2" date="2026-06-11">
      <description>
        <p>Performance polish — the applet does less redundant work:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The 24-hour graph no longer redraws itself as you move the mouse over the popup; it updates only when the weather, the hour, the time format, or the theme changes</li>
          <li>The panel icon appears immediately at startup instead of briefly waiting on a display-size check</li>
          <li>Typing in the refresh-interval and air-quality token settings no longer saves on every keystroke — changes are saved when you press Enter or close the popup</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.9.1" date="2026-06-11">
      <description>
        <p>Bug-fix patch hardening four rough edges:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Notifications with accented or non-ASCII alert text no longer crash the applet</li>
          <li>The pressure-unit setting is remembered correctly after a restart</li>
          <li>Switching location or refreshing quickly no longer briefly shows the previous location's weather</li>
          <li>Opening Settings or Alerts from inside the pollutants, pollen, or saved-locations views now returns to the chosen tab</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.9.0" date="2026-06-09">
      <description>
        <p>A new Graph tab draws a YR.no-style 24-hour meteogram: the temperature line over auto-scaled precipitation bars up top, sustained and gust wind below, with weather symbols, a now-marker, and shaded night hours across both panels. The Hourly tab now shows per-hour wind speed and precipitation amount. Both read from weathervane 0.5. And every June a thin Philadelphia eight-stripe pride flag runs across the top of the popup and under the panel readout, on by default with a toggle in Settings. Plus translation updates for Czech, Swedish, and Simplified Chinese.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.6" date="2026-06-07">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution change only, no code changes. Tempest is now self-distributed through the AUR and a self-hosted Flatpak remote, off the COSMIC Store.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.5" date="2026-05-19">
      <description>
        <p>Settings polish. The Location section now reads as a proper titled card like every other section in the tab, instead of a loose heading floating above its controls. Save-location and remove-saved-location icon buttons grow tooltips so it's obvious what they do. Sentence case across the Saved locations and Air quality headers in the en-US locale, matching the rest. Internal cleanup under the hood: the settings tab and the message dispatch were both heavy single-function blocks and got split along their natural seams, so adding a setting or wiring a new message touches one small place instead of scrolling through a few hundred lines.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.4" date="2026-05-15">
      <description>
        <p>Another COSMIC conformance pass. Settings tab sections render as proper titled cards now, matching cosmic-settings. The AQI and pollen rows in the Current tab read as tappable cards with chevron, replacing the flat text-button styling. Sub-view headers swap the X-close on the right for a back arrow on the left, since sub-views are drill-in pages and that's the convention every other COSMIC app uses. Panel button icons and the temperature label scale with the panel size tier instead of pinning to a single size. Popup header buttons get tooltips. The alerts header button drops the destructive red it was using to flag active alerts. Section headers move from caption-with-accent to title4, ALL CAPS settings labels drop to sentence case, and overuse of accent color on routine subtitles is pruned back. The Temperature, Measurement, and Pressure unit selectors get full width below their labels instead of being squeezed into the right half of a row.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.3" date="2026-05-14">
      <description>
        <p>Pollen forecast for European locations via CAMS, surfaced in the Current tab. The highest-severity active species leads, with a caption counting the rest, and a new Pollen sub-view breaks out every species with its grain count. Plus a COSMIC compliance polish in the popup. Text sizes pick up the cosmic typography role helpers instead of hand-rolled pixel values, so the scale tracks system theme changes. Scrollable surfaces in the popup and alert descriptions now reserve room for the scrollbar so it stops clipping content. The Forecast tab's header and rows share a single column-width contract, and the header reads as a heading rather than a caption. The saved locations sub-view picks up the same centered-title-with-close header that pollutants and pollen already use, so the three sub-views match.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.2" date="2026-05-13">
      <description>
        <p>Polish pass to bring the popup in line with the COSMIC design spec in Figma. The Air Quality view now leads with a centered title and a Close button on the right, replacing the old Back button on the left. Spacing and icon sizes across the popup, the alerts panel, and the loading and error states are tuned to match the reference. The popup is a touch narrower, and alert descriptions resize to fit instead of always reserving a fixed block of space. No new features and no changes to the data Tempest pulls or how it pulls it.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.1" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Popup adopts libcosmic's typography presets and list primitives. Text picks up theme-driven font weight and line-height, and lists render with the standard divider treatment instead of hand-rolled rows. Settings unit selectors collapse to the standard settings row. All remaining literal spacing values switch to cosmic-theme tokens. README rewritten for a technical audience.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.8.0" date="2026-04-22">
      <description>
        <p>Japan's current temperature now comes from JMA's AMeDAS ground station network for coordinates inside Japan, fixing the several-degree-cold readings Open-Meteo's blended model was giving. Air quality gets an optional aqicn.org token that sources from ground monitoring stations globally outside Europe. Europe stays on Open-Meteo to preserve the European AQI scale. No setup required for the Japan fix. The token is user-supplied and free.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.7.0" date="2026-04-09">
      <description>
        <p>Tempest is moving into maintenance mode after this release. Bug fixes and dependency catchup only, no new features planned.</p>
        <p>This release fixes an issue where the applet could get stuck after waking from suspend if NetworkManager didn't report the network change reliably. Tempest now listens for resume events directly and refreshes automatically without needing a manual retry.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.6.0" date="2026-03-22">
      <description>
        <p>Extracted all weather logic, API calls, and network monitoring into the tempest-core library crate. The applet is now a thin frontend over the shared library. No user-facing changes, but roughly 1,700 lines of duplicated code are gone. Translation updates from Weblate for Czech, Hungarian, Polish, Swedish, Ukrainian, and Simplified Chinese.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.5.0" date="2026-03-07">
      <description>
        <p>Saved locations and code cleanup. Bookmark up to 8 locations and switch between them from the popup header. Includes a code audit pass that streamlined panel rendering, converted manual loops to iterators, and removed dead i18n strings.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.4.3" date="2026-03-05">
      <description>
        <p>Connection retry and network-aware refresh. The applet now retries failed weather fetches with exponential backoff and listens to NetworkManager for instant refresh when connectivity is restored. HTTP requests have a 15-second timeout.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.4.2" date="2026-03-05">
      <description>
        <p>Migrated project to GitLab and added CI/CD pipeline for automated .deb builds on release tags</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.4.1" date="2026-02-27">
      <description>
        <p>Freezing precipitation support and translation updates</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added weather codes for freezing drizzle and freezing rain</li>
          <li>Updated translations for Czech, Chinese (Simplified), German, Hungarian, Polish, Portuguese (Brazil), Swedish, Ukrainian, and English (US)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.4.0" date="2026-02-23">
      <description>
        <p>Pressure unit selection and text overflow fix</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added pressure unit selector (hPa, inHg, PSI) in settings</li>
          <li>Auto-units now sets inHg for imperial countries</li>
          <li>Fixed long condition text overflowing the 7-day forecast widget border</li>
          <li>Routed remaining hardcoded strings through Fluent for localization</li>
          <li>Added Ukrainian metainfo and desktop translations</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.3.3" date="2026-02-20">
      <description>
        <p>Translation updates and metainfo localization</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added Portuguese (Brazil) translation</li>
          <li>Added Czech translation to appstream metainfo</li>
          <li>Added weather-fetch-error string to Czech, Hungarian, Polish, Swedish, and Chinese</li>
          <li>Refined Czech and Hungarian translation wording</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="2.3.2" date="2026-02-09">
      <description>
        <p>Security fixes and UI improvements</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Sanitized error messages to prevent coordinate leaks in screenshots</li>
          <li>Stripped HTML tags from alert notifications</li>
          <li>Widened popup to 520px</li>
          <li>Rebalanced forecast table columns</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Current weather conditions</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="cs">Aktuální stav počasí</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="uk">Поточні умови погоди</caption>
      <image>https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest/-/raw/main/screenshots/tempest-main.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Hourly weather forecast</caption>
      <image>https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest/-/raw/main/screenshots/tempest-hourly.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>7-day weather forecast</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="cs">Předpověď na 7 dní</caption>
      <caption xml:lang="uk">Прогноз погоди на 7 днів</caption>
      <image>https://gitlab.com/vintagetechie/cosmic-ext-applet-tempest/-/raw/main/screenshots/tempest-7day.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1">
    <content_attribute id="social-info">mild</content_attribute>
  </content_rating>

  <provides>
    <id>com.system76.CosmicApplet</id>
  </provides>
</component>
